<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The light of Gods countenance: or, The glory of God in the face of Ghrist [sic] Jesus infinitely out-shining all earthly vanities. Set out in a sermon preached at Lantilio Pertholy, in Monmouth-shire, June 5. 1653. By John Cragge, Master of Arts, and dispenser of the gospell there.</title>
            <author>Cragge, John, M.A.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34900</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6787</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R215238</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827173</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827173</idno>
            <idno type="VID">31589</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34900)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 31589)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1905:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The light of Gods countenance: or, The glory of God in the face of Ghrist [sic] Jesus infinitely out-shining all earthly vanities. Set out in a sermon preached at Lantilio Pertholy, in Monmouth-shire, June 5. 1653. By John Cragge, Master of Arts, and dispenser of the gospell there.</title>
                  <author>Cragge, John, M.A.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 23, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J.G. for Nath: Web and Will: Grantham, at the sign of the Bear in S. Paul's Church-yard, near the little north door,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Wales, Aberystwyth, Wales.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>God --  Attributes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Jayne Henley</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Jayne Henley</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:31589:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31589:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE LIGHT OF</hi> Gods Countenance: OR, THE GLORY OF GOD <hi>IN THE FACE OF</hi> GHRIST JESUS, Infinitely out-ſhining all earthly VANITIES.</p>
            <p>Set out in a Sermon preached at <hi>Lantilio Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholy,</hi> in <hi>Monmouth</hi>-ſhire, <hi>June</hi> 5. 1653.</p>
            <p>By JOHN CRAGGE, Maſter of Arts, and Diſpenſer of the GOSPELL there.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>JOHN 1.9.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MAT. 13.45, 46.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Kingdome of Heaven is like unto a Merchant man, ſeeking goodly Pearles, who, when he had found one Pearl of great price, he went and ſold all that he had, and bought it.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by J.G. for NATH: WEB and WILL: GRANTHAM, at the ſign of the Bear in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, near the little North door. 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:31589:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31589:2"/>
            <head>To my much honoured Friend Mr. <hi>William Williams,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Margaret Williams</hi> his Wife, Grace, Mercy, and Peace be multiplied.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>WORTHIES,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Preſent you here with a ſmall Token of my Love, and Thankfulneſſe, which may be worth your acceptation, not as mine, for ſo it's rude and homely; but as it's God's, a truth moſt deare, and precious: Diamonds are eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med not for the curioſity of cutting, but for their weight and worth; when you heard it, it affected the eare, and I (hope) the heart, which made you deſire a copy of it: I dare not quench the Spirit, but (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to promiſe) tender it to the eye, though not ſo ſoone as expected, yet perhaps in a dreſs unexpected.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Segnius irritant animum demiſſa per aurea.</l>
               <l>Quam quae ſunt oculis commiſſa fidelibus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> — Hor.</l>
            </q>
            <p>It containes a heavenly Jewell, in an earthly Cabinet, worth all the Arabian Gold, <hi>Indian</hi> Pearle, Riches of <hi>China,</hi> the wealth of the <hi>Weſt Indians</hi> company, or that which <hi>Solomons</hi> Navy brought from <hi>Tarſhiſh;</hi> for it's that one precious Rearle, <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for which the Merchant ſold all that he had, and bought it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chymiſts</hi> boaſt much of the <hi>Philoſophers Stone,</hi> that turnes all mettalls into Gold; <hi>Empericks</hi> of <hi>Aeſculſapius</hi> his Herbe <hi>Panaſe,</hi> that cures all diſeaſes; Warriers of <hi>Vulcans Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noplie,</hi> or Armour of proof againſt all weapons; Jewellers of the precious Stone, <hi>Opalum,</hi> that hath the vertue of all Stones; But here is an <hi>Elixir,</hi> or Quinteſcence, that turnes all things into Gold of the Sanctuary; an Herb of Grace, that cures all Soule-ſickneſſes; Chriſts whole Armorie, both offenſive, and defenſive, to ſhield againſt all ſpirituall enemies; a precious Corner Stone, that compriſes the vertue of all ſtones in the building of the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> nay it is the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> it ſelfe, from above, whoſe light is the Lambe, a light, which (if truely received) would quell Schiſme in Diſcipline, Hereſie in Doctrine, Sects in the Church, Factions in the State: Quench that <hi>Granado</hi> of Selfiſhneſs, and Pride, that rends the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall body of Chriſt in pieces. I can aſſure you in the Word of Life, and Truth, the richeſt and rarest confluence of all humane happineſſes, the most exquiſite excellency, and variety of the greateſt worldly pompe and splendour that ever the Sun ſaw, ſince the firſt moment of its
<pb facs="tcp:31589:3"/>creation, or ſhall look upon while it ſhines in heaven, is but duſt in the ballance to one graine of grace, it is but dung to an humble mind ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly enlightned, but with the fore-taſt, but of the leaſt glimpſe of that incomprehenſible endleſs glorie which ſhall ſhortly be revealed, it is all in the true valuation but as vaine ſmoake, which does not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vaniſh as it riſeth, it utterly loſeth it ſelfe at the higheſt, but alſo drawes teares from a mans eyes, nay at laſt, wrings the very heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strings of every impenitent ſoule, with that extreameſt everlaſting honour, which would burſt ten thouſand hearts, ſeriouſly and ſenſibly to think on it before hand; it is not onely vanity but vexation of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, let worldly wiſdome ſay what it will, and disparage them, who ſincerely by the help of the holy Ghoſt, hold a conſtant counter motion to the courſe of the world, and corrections of the time, that they may keep a good Conſcience, the richeſt Treaſure, the deareſt Jewell that ever the heart of man was acquainted with, who infinitely deſire ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be Religious than Rich, to be Good than Great, to enjoy the favour of God than the Soveraignty, and pleaſures of all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the Earth: yet aſſuredly, when all is ſaid, and ſummed up, it is onely the true feare of Gods bleſſed Name, a zealous forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for his Glory Goodneſſe, and good Cauſes, that at the laſt day ſhall truly beautifie and adorne both all other perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſufficiencies, and indeed, ſanctifie and bleſſe all publique Employment, and ſervices of State. Goe then in this golden meane betwixt Prophaneneſſe on the one hand, &amp; Singularity and Hypocriſie on the other; and yours ſhall be the crowne and comfort, when wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe ſhall lye buried in the duſt, and dungeon of hell. To this end the thirſty longing of my heart, and heartieſt prayers ſhall ever be, that you may ſhine every day more and more gloriouſly, in all perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſanctity, in all holy zeale, in ſetting forward the affaires of God, that when the last period of your mortall abode in this vale of tears, which drawes on apase, ſhall preſent it ſelfe; you may looke death in the face without doubt, the grave without feare, the Lord Jeſus with comfort, and <hi>Jehovah</hi> bleſſed for ever with everlaſting joy.</p>
            <p>That as God hath bleſſed you and your parents with the things of this life, he may bleſſe you and your poſterity with the treaſures of grace and the life to come, which are the ſerious votes of him, who will be for ever</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours to ſerve you, in the LORD JESUS, <hi>JOHN CRAGGE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:31589:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 4 6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>There be many that ſay, Who will ſhew us any good? Lord lift thou up the light of thy countenance upon us.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He heavenly language of this Pſalm informes us, That it was <hi>inspired by the holy Ghoſt;</hi> the Inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that it was <hi>penned by David;</hi> the matter, and manner in generall, that it was <hi>a comfortable ſob of a diſtreſſed ſoule in time of affliction.</hi> The ſtream of Interpreters, the whole courſe and current of the Text, his mixt paſſion of joy and ſorrow, diſtraction and conſolation, (as the pings of a woman in travell) compared with the Hiſtory in <hi>Samuel</hi> (as ſhreds of a broken veſſell laid one to another) tells us, that it was occaſioned by <hi>Sauls</hi> perſecuting of him after he was <hi>elected,</hi> and <hi>choſen King by Samuel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This will appeare more plainly by the parts, which are three; The firſt concernes God, and <hi>David,</hi> and that's a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precation, wherein he petitions God, that he would ſhield him from <hi>Saul</hi> and his complices. The ſecond concernes <hi>David</hi> and his enemies, for having made God his ſhield, he falls into an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulation with them in the ſecond verſe: the third verſe is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and apologie for himſelfe, being deeply ſlandered: the fourth and fift ſhew of what ſpirit he is, like Chriſt, that came out of his loynes, he ſpends his breath for their Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that ſought his Deſtruction. The third part is an earneſt prayer unto God againe for us, he was his <hi>Alpha,</hi> ſo he muſt be his <hi>Omega,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, beginning and ending (as the Serpent before the Fight drinks, when ſhe is wounded, runs to the Spring againe) runs to God the Fountaine of Living water, and ſo concludes thus the Analyſis.</p>
            <p>The Text is a parcell of the third part, and ſuch a principall one, as it gives denomination to all the reſt, a Petition; For as Prayer is an act of the nobler part of Man, the Soule, ſo it is to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:31589:4"/>be performed by the nobleſt, and moſt ſpirituall faculties of the ſouls. <hi>David</hi> here makes choice of the nobleſt and pureſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, Light, and of all Light, the nobleſt, <hi>the light of Gods counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</hi> And as the light of the Sunne is to the bodily eye, beſt knowne by Darkneſſe, the contrary; by effects the beams and heat of it: ſo is this ſpirituall light to the eye of the ſo ule. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>David</hi> proves the incomparable worth of it, 1. From an Argument drawn from an <hi>Antitheſis,</hi> or oppoſition with it, and all other Creatures, in the Text. 2. From the effects it works, which are two, 1. Spirituall comfort in the ſoule, <hi>ver.</hi> 7.2. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity and ſafety of both body and ſoule, <hi>ver.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Antitheſis</hi> in the words of the Text ſtands thus: As if he had ſaid, Let ſome ſwell with Pride, ſome boyle with Revenge, ſome burne with Luſt, ſome gaſpe for Honour, ſome gape for Riches, all ſweat, and toyle, and cling for Something, and ſome for All things, while the world is dealing her Legacies; yet none, nor all theſe, can give my Soule content; there is <hi>unum neceſſariam,</hi> One onely neceſſary thing, which neither Prince nor People, Men nor Angels, have in their keeping; Height nor Depth, Principalities nor Powers, Life nor Death, can take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, which makes my Prayers break thorow the Clouds towards Heaven, importunes God to bow down the Heavens, and come downe into my heart; <hi>Lord life up the light of thy countenance upon us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The diviſion of the Text we have pre-occupated in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text, which you ſee is an <hi>Antitheſis,</hi> or oppoſition betwixt the Worldlings wiſh, and the Saints wiſh; the Worldlings wiſh in theſe words, <hi>There be many that will ſay, who will ſhew us any good?</hi> The Saints wiſh, in theſe, <hi>Lord lift up the light of thy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance upon us.</hi> This will be made more clears from the parts: 1. Conſider the oppoſition betwixt the Subjects, or parties who, the children of the World, and the children of Light. 2. The quantity, the multitude of the one, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, many that ſay; the paucity and ſcantling of the other, but <hi>David,</hi> and ſome few that tread in his foot-ſtepts, that we can ſcarce trace them out. 3. The Object, or divers wiſhes, The Worldlings wiſh is like Himſelfe, <hi>Momentaris, fading, temporaris traſh, any good;</hi> The Sames wiſh like unto God, <hi>grate, favour, the light of his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:31589:4"/>an inheritance laid up in heaven, an everlaſting good.</hi> 4. The modality or manner. The Worldling onely <hi>ſayes,</hi> the Saint <hi>prayes;</hi> the Worldling, as he would have <hi>any good,</hi> ſo he cares not from what hand, <hi>who will,</hi> &amp;c. the Saint, as he would have the chief good, ſo onely from the hand of God, <hi>Lord lift,</hi> &amp;c. The Worldlings wiſh is propounded interogatively, full of <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, distraction, diſtruſt, despaire;</hi> the Saints wiſh is preferred in an humble petition before the <hi>Throne of grace, full of faith, Hope, confidence, and spirituall conſolation, Lord life,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now we ſhould paſſe from the Div ſion to Obſervations, but that the words are to be unfolded, for clearer underſtanding of the matter, there be many: Many is alwayes a note of Univerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and ſometimes taken ſo univerſally, as it includes all, excludes none, Rom. 5.19. <hi>By the diſobedience of One many are made ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> that is, all men: ſometimes for a great number ſimply con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, yet but a few compared with others, <hi>By the obedience of ſome many ſhall be made righteous,</hi> that is, a great number ſaved, yet but a few in compariſon of Reprobates. 3. It ſignifies the moſt and greateſt part of men: Mat. 7.13. <hi>Wide is the gate that leadeth to deſtruction, and many there be that enter in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt ſenſe, to ſay that all men wiſhed thus, were not charity; in the ſecond, to ſay theſe Worldlings were but few in compariſon of Saints, were neither truth nor piety; in the third, to ſay they are many in compariſon of Saints, agrees with Scripture, truth, experience, and the true meaning of this place.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That ſay:</hi> Saying ſometimes imports an act of the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, when one thinks ſo; of the Will, when one deſices ſo; of the Affection, when one inordinately deſires, properly of the tongue when they expreſſe that in words, which they think and deſire with the heart. All this ſuits with this place, with all worldlings, their Thoughts are wholly taken up, their Wills wholly bent, their Affections ſet a whoring after the things of this world, and ſometimes out of abundance of the heart the tongue will not ſtick to ſpeak as much; and if many ſay ſo, more think ſo: And though men carry not their hearts on their tongues ends, it is hard to think ſo alwayes, and never to ſpeak ſo. No children but they that want their due conception, or ſtill-borne,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:31589:5"/>but they cry at the birth, no vile thoughts but thoſe that are choa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in the heart, by grace, but will ſometimes be uttered by the tongue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who?</hi> This note of interrogation ſometimes hath the force of negation, and denyes more ſtrongly than a plaine negation would do, as pſal. 76.7. <hi>Who may ſtand in thy ſight when once thou art angry?</hi> That's none.</p>
            <p>And true it is, that ſuch is the wavering diſtruſt, and bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe wiſhes of Worldlings, that they are often times wracked with deſpaire of ever receiving good; and if they enjoy it, it's but in handling a feather, in fight a ſhadow, in weight a ſmoak, in opening an Image of plaiſter-work, nay plaine nothing: But this is not the meaning: <hi>Quis?</hi> Who? (ſayes <hi>Piſcator</hi>) is as much, as <hi>O ſi quis,</hi> O that any would, optatively, and in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, this jumps with the former, for oftentimes, where there are the greateſt Wiſhes, there are the greateſt Wants, nay greateſt deſpaire. And here we may obſerve, an implyed dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution: 1. <hi>O ſi quis, O that any would;</hi> as if it were but wiſh and have: then a <hi>Si quis,</hi> or Proclamation, <hi>if any will;</hi> then (as if he were at a loſſe) interrogatively, <hi>Quis?</hi> Who will? What Prince? what People? what Man? what Angel? what Saint? what Reprobates? nay, before they ſtick out, what Devill? ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than their hands be empty, with <hi>Ahaziah</hi> will goe to <hi>Beel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zebub,</hi> the God of <hi>Ecron,</hi> for Health, with <hi>Saul</hi> to the Witch for Counſell, with thoſe of <hi>Lapland,</hi> ſo they arrive at their Wiſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for port, buy wind of the Devill, if their ſoules will purchaſe it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shew,</hi> that is, performe, it hath relation to the word <hi>(ſay)</hi> going before, and muſt anſwer to it, as if he ſhould ſay preſent to our underſtandings, conſent to our Wills, ſatisfie our Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcences, performe that indeed which we affect with the Heart, and deſire with the Tongue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Any.</hi> This word <hi>(any)</hi> is not found in the Originall, yet it is implyed here, and written in every Worldlings heart, which, as it makes the propoſition indefinit, ſo it argues their luſts are infinit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Good,</hi> The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> too, here in the Originall, is ſometimes put for that which is Pleaſant, ſometimes for that which is Profitable, as for that which is Good, as they either pleaſe or profit, of Concupiſcence,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:31589:5"/>Beauty, Bravery, diſports of Ambition, Honour, Pomp, Glory, of covetouſneſſe, Riches, Lands, Revenewes; all or ſome of theſe have a fanne, that winnowes nothing out, <hi>All is fiſh that comes to net.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much for the opening of the words in the former part of the Text; before we proceed, let us build up this we have cut downe: the point of Doctrine wee'l raiſe from this foundation is this, That Many, even the greateſt part of the world, are who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, diſorderly, diſtractedly, exceedingly bewitched, and taken up with the things of this world; or (if you pleaſe) thus, That there is an over-ruling Concupiſcence in the ſoules of moſt men, for Faculties univerſall, for Degrees extenſive, for Meaſure end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, dragging them after the things of this world, as their main, and architectonicall end.</p>
            <p>That we have builded no more upon this Foundation than the words will beare, firſt that the Text ſhall prove, then afterwards we will prove the Text.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the greateſt part of men are poſſeſt with this epide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micall diſeaſe, that here they are ſaid to be <hi>many,</hi> compared with <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.13. Many <hi>there be that enter in at the broad gate:</hi> And <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.16. Many <hi>are called, but few choſen,</hi> makes it plaine, where <hi>many</hi> is oppoſed to <hi>few:</hi> But how many does <hi>David</hi> mean? To ſay nothing that he was now in perſecution, in baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, where none durſt be ſeen in his defence, none durſt ſpeak in his behalfe; it is to be feared he had as few favourers of his Doctrine as of his Fortune, and thoſe that are not with him, are againſt him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That it is a leproſie of the ſoule that hath univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally ſpread through all the faculties, appeares in that they ſay ſo; for as books that are printed, <hi>cum privilegio,</hi> pre-ſuppoſes that they have beene examined, reviewed, approved by the Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tators: ſo when men expreſſe themſelves outwardly, it's preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med they conſent inwardly: True it is, that hypocrites may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe, ſpeake better, and think worſe, but on the other ſide, we may be ſure that in this, <hi>concluſio ſequitur deteriorem partem,</hi> if men ſpeak ill, they think as ill, or worſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That their ſoules are winded up to a high pitch of Concupiſcence, exteramely bewitched with theſe Vanities,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:31589:6"/>appears by this diſtracted Interrogation, <hi>Quis! Who will?</hi> For as ſparkling Iron pulled out of the Smiths Forge, ſhews the Fornace is hot, ſo theſe wiſhes the paſſionate Rhetorique of a diſtracted ſoule; one while breathing out Hope, another while Deſpaire, (like the tranſes of a phrenſie, or the fits of a Fever) ſhews that the forge of the Affections does extreamly boyle.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, that their luſts are boundleſs and endleſſe, is ſhewn in this, That they hunger after <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> any good; for as thoſe greedy ſtomacks that revennouſly devoure any meat, have the dog-like appetite, and can never be ſatisfied; ſo thoſe that goe a whoring after <hi>all things,</hi> cannot be ſatisfied with <hi>any thing,</hi> but as cold drink given in a hot feaver, increaſe the ſcorching.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, That they make them their architectionical end, and the only mark they aime at; may be proved, 1. from an oppoſition implyed in the Text, for if they long after any good, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not attaine the chief good; Chriſt tells us we cannot love <hi>God and Mammon:</hi> 2. From the weakneſſe of the faculties of our ſoule, as thoſe that would know the bigneſſe of a Starre, or the proportion and colour of any thing a farre off, ſuffers not their eyes to gaze abroad, but looks thorow their perſpective glaſſes; ſo thoſe that would look up at God, a brightneſſe of glory that no mortall eye can ſee, muſt not fix their ſpirituall eyes upon the things of this world, as Honour, Profit, Pleaſure, for if they doe, they will never pierce the clouds.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee the Text affords the point without ſtrainig, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wreſting: now wee will prove it: 1: In particular, then in generall, by Teſtimonie, by Scripture.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to prove the ſubject of the Queſtion (which every Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence takes for granted) that there are worldlings, or worldly-minded men, were as needleſſe, as for a man in the world, while he beheld the Heavens that encompaſſed him, the Starres that gave him light to go about, to prove there were a world, or for a man that was toſſed in the midſt of the Sea, and could ſee no Land to prove there were a Sea.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That there are many worldlings ariſes from the former, as one link of a chain joyned to another; if a Leproſie hath infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted a part, it will ſpread over the whole; when a Gangreen hath ſeized upon one limb, the reſt can ſcarce eſcape putrefacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:31589:6"/>if there be carnall and worldly-minded men, there will be many; and whilſt the ſeeds of this corruption lies within all, apt to be kindled by any ſpark, diſpoſed by nature, and kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled by imitation, one Beacon gives warning to the reſt. All Scriptures, all ages, men of all conditions, have given incontroul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able evidence to this truth, Scriptures, Prophets, Apoſtles, Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts have foretold, reproved, dehorted from this multitude. All ages before the Floud, many thouſands firſt ſpiritually drowned in Adultery, Fornication, Uuncleanneſs, Laſciviouſneſs, after bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the waters, onely eight that forſook the world, and eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the floud. Since the floud till Chriſt, who ſtood in oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the world, he found but twelve that would forſake it, and one of them a Devill. Since Chriſt, in theſe laſt dayes, as laſt ſo worſt and moſt perilous moſt men <hi>lovers of Pleaſure more than lovers of God,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.1. Men of all conditions, Jews, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, Turks, Pagans, Chriſtians, Young, Old, Rich, Poor, ſo many, that while we cite all to bring in evidence, we ſhall ſcarce finde any to be judge or witneſs, that is not a party not partiall. Thus you ſee the multitude.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That all the powers of the ſoule are poſſeſſed with it, and that in a high degree it's as eaſie to prove; we will inſtance only in the voluptuous man, for the point is ſo large, and the time ſo ſhort, that we muſt examine one for all the reſt. To begin with his underſtanding, for there all vanities enters aboard, and loſes anchor, it's wholly occupied (as <hi>Phalaris</hi> was in new torments) in inventing new pleaſures to delight the Eye, Arbors, Orchards, ſtately Buildings: to delight the Palate, new Junkets, Meats, Drinks, Wines; new Recreations in their Sports, Playes, Revel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. Now the underſtanding once kindled, though (like a match) it be but ſlow in burning, when it preſents but the leaſt ſpark to the will, it's up aloft (as a train of Gun powder) <hi>dicto citius,</hi> one faculty inflames another, till the whole man be in a combuſtion, and that ſo fiercely, ſo furiouſty, ſo outragiouſly, that neither Reaſon nor Scripture, Counſels nor Reproofs, Fear nor ſhame, can reclaime them: Thus you ſee the univerſality and extremity of it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That their luſts and labours are endleſs, in purſuing theſe va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, as their onely end, we need not toyle to prove, as before in the voluptuous: We will inſtance now in the Covetous Man,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:31589:7"/>whereof the one thinks the other the greateſt fool in the world, the one for ſparing, the other for ſpending; and yet the Seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture calls them both fooles. O conſider how the caresof the world ruſh upon them, in the morning as ſoon as they awake, accompany, and rack them in the day, ſcare them in the night, follow them to bed, hinder them from ſleep, affright them in their dreames; and for what? to build ſtately Houſes, purchaſe. Lands, heap up Riches, procure Dgnities, make Marriages, joyn Kindreds, as though there were no Death, no Grave, no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, no Judgement, no God, no Devill, no Heaven, no Hell hereafter.</p>
            <p>Thus it is proved in patricular; a word or two in generall, and we will paſſe on Firſt by the teſtimony of Heathen men, that had but the lgith Nature; of the Apoſtles, that had the light of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration; of Chriſt, that was the light it ſelfe; and ſo we have found the Spring.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That Heathen men that were of the world ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry this enormity of the world, and they that were blind-fold ſhould eſpy others go aſtray, had been a wonder, if it were not ſo palpable, ſo univerſall, ſo extream, that the very blind might grope it; that well might <hi>Juvenall</hi> ſay, <hi>Prima fere vota, &amp; tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis notiſſima templis, divitiae ut Creſcant,</hi> Every mans firſt wiſh's, firſt prayers are, when he enters into Church, that riches may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creale. Were it a ſatyre, or too harſh a reproof to ſay ſo in thereſe dayes? The truth is, our Doctrine now is farre purer than the Heathens were, but in point of practice we differ little; I doe not ſpeak of all, but as my Text leads me, of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>many.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Of the Apoſtles, take one for all, 1 John 2.16. <hi>All that is in the World, is, the luſt of the Fleſh, the luſt of the Eyes, and pride of Life.</hi> Luſt of the Fleſh as carnall Recreations, Banqueting, Laughing, Playing; luſt of the Eyes, Riches, Wealth, Profits; pride of Life, as vain Glory. Promotion, Nobility, carnall Wiſdome, Beanty, exceſs in Apparrell: theſe almoſt ſhare the world a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them; if there be ſome Saints of purer metall, it is but like a veine of Gold mixt with much Droſs, none pure and alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether refined, but thoſe triumphant in Haven.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, let him witneſſe this, that mnſt judge us all, our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, amongſt that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or throng of ſutors that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:31589:7"/>preſs'd upon him while he ſojourn'd here, how many ſurd forthis world? how few for the world to come? Indeed ſome troubled with Iſſues of Blood, Lepers, Blind, Lame, Dumb, Lunatick, poſſeſs'd with Devils came to him; but for clenſing originall Sin, leproſie of the Soul, blindneſs of the Heart, lameneſs of the Affections, ſpirituall Phrenſies, caſting out legions of Iniquities; he had almoſt as few Suitors in his Life, as Reſcuers at his Death: There came indeed two or three to him, to ask what they ſhould do to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Heaven, being told that they muſt ſell their Goods, forſake the World (as that Cardinall that would not forego his part in <hi>Paris</hi> for that in <hi>Paradiſe</hi>) they forſook Chriſt and clove to the World. The <hi>Jewes</hi> hoped, the <hi>Romans</hi> feared, <hi>Herod</hi> was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, <hi>Caeſar</hi> was diſquieted, his Enemies were jealous, his Friends and Apoſtles ſtood expecting, and all but for a temporall Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy; when that failed, they failed, onely a Thief that was nayled with im ſticked to him; and what thanks was that to him, now to contemn (and crucify the world) that had already condemned and crucified him? Thus the proof in generall ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments and reaſions, farther to confirm it, may be four:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt is drawn from the Worldings ignorance; many make choice of theſe vanities, highly prize them, earneſtly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue them, reſt in them being got, becauſe they know no better: our Eyes are blind, our Eares deaf, our Underſtandings darkned, our Hearts dull, our Affections dead, our Conſciences ſeared, that they cannot diſcern ſpirituall things, God, Glory, and Life everlaſting. This Chriſt witneſſes with his Word to the worman of <hi>Samaria, Si noſſes petiiſſes,</hi> if thou hadſt known thou wouldſt have asked: With his teares over <hi>Jereſalem: Luke</hi> 19.42. <hi>O ſi noſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes!</hi> Othat thou hadſt known <hi>the things that belong to thy peacel</hi> By his pangs in his Agony, <hi>Si noſſent,</hi> if they had <hi>known,</hi> they would not have crucified the Lord of Glory. Butlwhat then? becauſe we are blind in ſpirituall, are we therefore quick ſighted in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall things? becauſe we know no God, ſhall we know and proze the World the more? Yes: Owles and Bats that cannot ſee in the day, are ſo much quicker in the night: Noals that have not eyes to look up to heaven, are the beſt armed for digging in the earth: Mans ſoul is a diſcouerſing creature, that muſt needes bring concluſions from ſome premiſſes, if it know to better
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:31589:8"/>than the world, it will conclude the world is beſt. God and his Word ſhould be the food of our ſoule; but for lack of that, like a greedy diſtempred ſtomach, it will feed upon any thing, even (as the diſeaſe the wolfe) upon the corruptions of our own fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy fleſh. The Philoſophers reaſon concludes here, the Sphinx and Eagle are quicker in ſight, the Vultur in ſmelling, the Spider in touching, and ſo in the reſt, than man (though he be of a nobler complexion) becauſe nature hath bounded them there, induing him farther with reaſon; which darkens the inferiour faculties, as the Sun the reſt of the Starres: ſo if Gods grace ſhine in our hearts, all worldly glory is darkned, Beauty ſeemes a painted ſnaile, Riches but vanity, Honour but a blaſt of idle winde: But if we make this brittle, glaſſy world (which ſhould be our Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective, and ſpectacles to look up towards Heaven) our looking-glaſs; our own vanities will reflect upon our eyes, as <hi>Pigmalion</hi> with his picture, or <hi>Narciſſus</hi> with his own ſhadow, we ſhall dout upon our ſelves, the world, and the fleſh.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond reaſon is drawn from our indiſtinct knowledge; for though we know heavenly things in part, yet ſo fully, ſo plenarily, ſo diſtinctly, as theſe below; what man amongſt us ſo ignorant, ſo bruitiſh that hath not heard of Heaven? cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Heavn? ſometimes thinks not of Heaven? meditates not that there will come a day of death, of judgement? that our life will vaniſh away as a ſmoak, as a vapour, as a dreame? and as death leaves us, ſo judgement will finde us. But alas, this Knowledge is but Ignorance, cannot diſtinguiſh us from Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, nay, from Devils; they know more of this by contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, by obſervation, than we: here is the default, that it is not grounded in the Underſtanding, ſettled in the Affections, wrought into the heart, eſtabliſhed in the Conſcience; this is the true and diſtinct knowledge, and what our knowledge hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definite of ſpirituall, it will have in exceſs of temporall: This ariſes from the diſproportion and distance betwixt our ſouls and ſpiritual things, from the proportion and nearneſs betwixt them, and temporall; they are continually in our ſight, fills our eyes more, affects us deeplyer, and though they be like the Moon, now w<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xing, now wayning, now eclipſed, now altogether gone; yet becauſe they are neareſt us, they ſeem bigger than Grace,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:31589:8"/>Mercy, Peace, and other fixed Starres in the firmament of glory.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third reaſon to prove the wee are paſſionately carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after the things of this world, is drawn from the cauſe, which in generall is the corruption, and depravation of our nature, and the improvement of theſe curſed ſeeds in particular to every un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate man, who can bring Light out of Darkneſs, gather Grapes of Thornes, and Figgs of Thiſtles?</p>
            <p>Who being earthly, can deſire any thing but earthly? it is Chriſts own ſaying, Joh. 3.31. <hi>Qui ex terrâ, terrena</hi> &amp;c. <hi>He that is of the earth is earthly, and ſpeaks of the earth;</hi> nay, he not only ſpeaks of it, but he thinks of it, dreams of it, twings, and galls, and toyles his ſoule for it; places his health, his wealth, his feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city in it, that men are become like brambles, growing with both ands into the ground: as waſpes can reliſh nothing but poyſon, as ſpiders weave webbs out of nothing but the principles of our corrupted nature; as amber draws nothing but ſtubble, traſh, and ſtraw unto us: Luſt raignes in the throne of the fleſh, the world beſieges it; Satan ſtrives to be the Porter; theſe three are the Tritarkes of the Soule, that either bribes or caſts Conſcience in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſleep, ſuffering the Will, Underſtanding, and Affections to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine no gueſt, till they have firſt ſworne Allegiance to them: hence is that diſorder in the ſoule, diſtempered heat of a feavour, now carking, now cating, now burning, now boyling, now lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, now loathing, ſtill coveting, never ſatisfied.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Fourthly, the generall example of others, and daily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing with them, begets in men an eſteem, that ſome unvalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble excellency is in them: All places ſeem to worſhip this Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, or Idoll of the World; Towns, Viliages, Countries, Cities, Courts, &amp; Common-wealths makes ſuits for this; Debates in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Pleas, upper Bench, Chancery, Court of Wards; Trialls for Lands, Goods, Liberty, Honour pleads anſwer to this interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, <hi>Who will ſhew us any good?</hi> Men ventures themſelves on the angry Seas, diggs into the bowels of the Earth, expoſes their bodyes in wars to Wounds, Scarrs, Schirmages, Maſſakers, Death, for Honor, Riches, Wealth, Empire, Dignity; the Young man hopes, the Strong man enjoyes, the O d feares to loſe them, the Poore ſorrowes for them, the Rich rejoyces in them, and yet ſtill craves more; an Earldome, a Dukedome, a Kingdome, an Empire,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:31589:9"/>nay, if the whole would could be granted; ſuch is the boundleſs ambition of man, that he would weep with <hi>Alexander,</hi> that there were no more worlds to be conquered but one; nay, for this they will ſweare, lye, deceive, oppreſſe, extort, toyl Body, wound Soul, gall and gaſh Conſcience, and are not ſo many examples by Sea, Land, Young, Old, Rich, Poor, able to draw a world after them? Hitherto the reaſons, the uſes follow, 1. Of information:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu</hi> And, <hi>Whether it be lawfull, agreeable to Gods will, any prejudice to the health of the Soule, to deſire theſe tempor all things or no?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The truth is, we may: for all good is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>quaſi</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> amiable, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, very divine, having ſome ſparke of Gods Image in it; goods temporall, ſpirituall, internall, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, eternall for this life, for the life to come.</p>
            <p>Are all attractive, deſirable in their places, in their order? 1. Becauſe they are Gods Creatures which are all good, all for ſome uſe: 2. Becauſe God hath implanted in us, by nature, a deſire of them; <hi>omne appetit bonum,</hi> every thing deſires that which is good, and nothing is deſired but that which is good or ſeemes to be ſo, in that we call evill good, deſire it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively, diſorderly; it came by corrupted nature, not by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: 3. Becauſe we cannot live without them; they are ſcrips, and baggs that we muſt uſe in our pilgrimage to the heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> barques that muſt ferry us over <hi>Jordan</hi> to the Land of <hi>Promiſe:</hi> 4. They are meanes whereby we may ſerve God with more cheerfulneſſe here, in providing helpes, diſtributing to the neceſſity of Saints, charitably ſuccouring the poor; 5. They are meanes to further us in our journy to heaven; for if in the creatures here below, we deſcry Beauty, Goodneſs, Glory: O then how good, how beautifull, how glorious is He that made them? But now, as the world uſes them, they are become thorns, ſtumbling-blocks, impediments, hinderances for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: and that in theſe three reſpects,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, <hi>Ratione ordinis,</hi> when we deſires them diſorderly, as children that delight themſelves with the guilded out-ſide of the book, and look not within, or as ſwine that feed upon the acrons and look not up at the tree, look not up at God (except as Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners at the pole) that thereby they may better arrive at their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:31589:9"/>earthly ſhore; deſire riches, honour as their chief felicity and end, not as meanes leading to that end: this made our Saviour direct and preſcribe the right order, Mat. 6 33. <hi>Seek firſt the Kingdome of GOD, and the righteouſneſs thereof, and other things ſhall be added unto you,</hi> for Body, for Soul, for Health, for Wealth, for this Life as well as for the Life to come: but if the things of this life that ſhould be Gods Embaſſadours, Souldiers, Ledgers, Factors, rob him of his Glory, and challenge Soveraignty to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, though with <hi>Abſolom</hi> they may ſeduce, flitter, and b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witch for a time, yet this treaſon will be puniſhed, and attach the worldlings conſcience, that neither Field, nor towne, nor Bed, nor Board, nor Life, nor Death, nor Depth, nor Grave can render them ſecure.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, the things of this world become hurtfull, <hi>reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctu medi,</hi> when they are deſired out of meaſure exceſſively, when the underſtanding too highly prizes them, the will too earneſtly deſires them, the affections (like Souldiers about a prey) are at jatre amongſt themſelves, and at mutiny with God for them, crying paſſionately with the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for <hi>Manna,</hi> or <hi>Rachael, Gen.</hi> 30.1. <hi>Da liberos, Give mee Children or I die.</hi> This is, 1. when we deſire them without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, not ſubmitting our will to Gods will: 2. without bounds, that our whole ſoule is taken up with them, that faith, zeale, charity are expelled: 3. without end, that if all worldly contentment ſhould flow upon them, as Rivers into the Sea, yet the boundleſſe bank of their ambition would never be filled.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the third place, the things of this world become hurtfull, <hi>reſpectu mediorum,</hi> when they care not by what means, ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, lying, fraud, guile, couſenage, oppreſſion, extortion, <hi>dum potiantur modò,</hi> ſo they may get them; rob Belly, Back, Wife, Children, Friends, Kinsfolks; ſuch the blood of Orphans, oppreſs the Widow, grind the face of the Poore, uſe falſe Weights and Meaſures, deceitfull Billances, ſpeak like Angels, practiſe like Devills, have ravenous clawes under their Harpyes ſaces, Peacocks feathers, Dragons tayles, care not what point in the compaſſe that winde blowes, what Religion be profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſo it bring them profit: In a word, forgoe Credit,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:31589:10"/>Soule, Conſcience, Heaven, and Salvation for them.</p>
            <p>The ſecond uſe ariſing from the premiſſes, may ſerve to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove three ſorts of men:</p>
            <p>Firſt, Thoſe that make Mammon their God, Wealth their Felicity, reſt here in things below, as if they had an abiding City; Whether ſhall we now firſt chide, or weep to ſee that foretold by S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2. in theſe laſt dayes come to paſſe, Men Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of their own ſelves, Covetous, Boaſters, Proud, Heady, high-minded, <hi>more men lovers of Pleaſure than lovers of God:</hi> Would it not make one's heart to bleed, to ſee Chriſtians in name, live Epicures lives in deed, <hi>eat, drink and be merry, for to morrow we ſhall die;</hi> like the fool in the Goſpel, ſing Requiems to their ſouls. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.19. <hi>Scule, thou hast goods laid up for many yeares, live at eaſe, eat, drinke, and be merry;</hi> with <hi>Achitophel</hi> truſt in Policy, with <hi>Senacharib</hi> in ſtrength of Armies, ſacrifice to their own nets, and draggs, never ſincerely think of God, alwayes think of the World, and though they ſeem firſt to pray for ſpiritual things, and afterwards for temporall, their affections reades them back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards like figures, valuing the latter ten times more than the former.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this reproves and laſhes thoſe, if they have not inward laſhes enough, that torment themſelves with carking, and will never be ſatisfied, that enlarge their deſires as Hell, as Hell in deſiring all, end leſſe, infinite, receive Hell into their Soules here, and without repentance be received for ever into Hell hereafter. Ah Brethren! to ſee in many, how this care breaks the Leggs, looſes the Joynts, conſumes the Marrow, burns up the Spirits, dries up the Moyſture, wounds their Hearts, deads their Soules, and murders their Conſciences.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, this reproves thoſe that care not who trouble the Water, God, Angels, Devils, or Men, ſo they be cured; come preferment from Eaſt, Weſt, or South, ſo they enjoy it: Let <hi>Joſeph</hi> lie in Priſon, <hi>Daniel</hi> in the Lions Denne, the three Children in the hot fiery Fornace; ſo they laugh, quaffe with <hi>Belſhazar,</hi> fare deliciouſly with the rich Glutron, oppreſſe with <hi>Zacheus,</hi> lie to their owne Conſciences with <hi>Ananias,</hi> ſo they may enjoy their darling pleaſure, profitss, delights; with <hi>Felix, Agrippa, Feſtus,</hi> forſake Chriſt for the preſent world; betray
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:31589:10"/>Father, Mother, Brother, Siſter, deareſt Friend for gaine, Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Seduce, Crouch, looke Bigge, uſe courteous Equivocations, carry many Faces under one hood, with <hi>Judas</hi> betray our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour for money: O that many mens conſciences did not wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe this! I ſay, O that Countryes, Villages, Townes, Cities, Markets, Fayers, publique Courts, and private Families did not teſtifie this!</p>
            <p>The third uſe ſhould ſerve to examine our ſoules, whether we be of this number that thus prepoſterouſly, exceſſively, by inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate meanes ſtand for the world, or no? But alas! the ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptomes and diſaſterous effects it works (if every mans conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence would give up a bill) ſhewes the diſeaſe is too epidemicall: let us rather uſe means for the cure, firſt ripping up the ſore, then apply the ſalve.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt conſider all things of this world, ſeparated from Chriſt, are but vanities: Let the ambitious mans pride be a looking glaſſe for this, ſee how he robs all creatures to adorne his body, from one takes his Wooll, from another his Skin, from another his Furre, from another his Excrements, as Silke from Wormes, beggs Pearles of Fiſhes, diggs into the ground for Gold and Silver, turnes up the ſands of the Sea for precious Stones; then Peackock-like, pride themſelves in theſe, which are but liveries of Beaſts, skum of the Earth, badges of Sinne, earneſts of Death, and recogniſants of Hell. And as theſe, ſo Riches, Honour, Wealtth, are but vaine: Why ſhould we then cark for them?</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But you will ſay, how can we live in credit with out this inordinate carking?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes: What if thou goe bare? wholſoms Frize is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than infected Velvet. What though thou fare hard? drye Bread is better than poyſoned Dainties. What though thy childred be kept Short? It is better to pinch them than to feed them with blood. What if thou muſt yet come lower? It is better to fall into the Duſt, than into Hell with the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, they are not onely vanities, but alſo deceits, that Promiſe faire, but performe nothing; golden Apples of <hi>Sodom,</hi> a deceitfull <hi>Laban,</hi> a falſe Merchant, a cunning Fiſher,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:31589:11"/>that layes pleaſant Baits on dangerous Hooks, a Strumpet of <hi>Babilon</hi> that gives poyſoned Drinks in golden Cups, an alluring <hi>Jaeb</hi> a flattering <hi>Joab,</hi> betraying <hi>Judas:</hi> Goe over the whole world, behold Counties, view Provinces, looke into Cities, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at the Doores, and Windows of private Houſes, of Princes Palaces, of ſecret Chambers, and you ſhall heare nothing but lamentable complaints; one for what he hath loſt, another for what he hath not wonne, a third for that he is not ſatisfied, ten thouſand for that they are deceived.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, as they are Deceits, ſo they are alſo Torments that afflict the Body, wound the Soule, gall and gaſh Conſcience; they bring vexation of Thoughts, tribulation of Feares, pricking of Cares, unquietneſſe of Soule, Flyes of <hi>Egypt,</hi> grapes of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> cluſters of <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> gall of Dragons, poyſon of Cockatri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce; that brings a Curſe with them that will be a Canker in thy wealth, a Moth in thy richeſt Garment, a Worme in thy talleſt Cedar, a Ruſt in thy pureſt Gold, which one day, as the phren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of <hi>Caine,</hi> deſpaire of <hi>Judas,</hi> madneſſe of <hi>Achitophel,</hi> trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of <hi>Felix,</hi> will dump all thy delights; who therefore, if the whole World were a Globe of Gold the Earth a Center of Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond; if the Heavens poured downe Balme, and the Cloudes ſhowred downe precious Oyntment, if Sea and Land, Sun and Starres payed tribute, and every yeare that went about, ſtrove to crowne them with Goodneſs, who (I ſay) would ſhackle his ſoule within that ſtinking Dungeon of this World, but would rather look through the grates and creviſes of the fleſh at God, a fixed Starre of glory, farr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> above any moveable Firmament. So we have done with the former part of the Text, this point, we paſſe on to the latter, <hi>Lord lift thou up,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Theſe words are an <hi>Epiphonema,</hi> occaſioned by the premiſſes, partly Declamatory, inveighing againſt the folly of the World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, partly Acclamatory, petitioning God, partly Conſolato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, comforting the Saints in the perſon of <hi>David.</hi> By this <hi>Aſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deton</hi> here, that theſe words are coupled to the former by no diſtructive note, as <hi>but Lord,</hi> are <hi>yet Lord:</hi> we may obſerve the Divine Rhetorick, and Suador of the Spirit, as by the Matter, ſo by the Manner, implying that there is no more compariſon betwixt God and Mammon, than there is betwixt Light and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:31589:11"/>Darkneſſe: Hence two points of Doctrine implyed might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, if you look back at the Antecedent <hi>this:</hi> though the World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings be high in Dignity, glorious in Title, infinite in Number, yet they are not to be followed; if forward at the Conſequence, <hi>this;</hi> that there is a Pearle in Gods keeping, for gaining of which, all worldly things are to be trodden under foot: but we muſt leave theſe as leſſer Starres, hid under a cloud: we come to that which is expreſſed, <hi>The light of Gods Countenance,</hi> a Starre able to ſet all mortall eyes on Earth immortall in Heaven at a gaze, at a maze: <hi>Lift thou up the Light,</hi> &amp;c. There is no darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the words, unleſſe too much light dazle our eyes: it is a ſpeech borrowed from men that uſe to caſt a lightſome Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance upon thoſe they favour or affect, as though he ſhould ſay, O Lord affect our Soules, raviſh our Spirits with the ſenſible fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of thy Favour, Grace, and Bleſſing that flowes from thee: Hence iſſues this point of Doctrine, that the Grace of God, and the Light of his Countenance, is a Bleſſing beyond all prices un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valuable, beyond all contradictions impregnable, beyond all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions tranſcendet, beyond all compariſons ſuperlatively great.</p>
            <p>Every word in the Text hath a ſpeciall Emphaſis to prove this; <hi>Lord,</hi> the word in the Originall is <hi>Jehovah,</hi> compoſed of ſpirtuall letters, to note the ſpirituall ſimplicity of his infinite Being, a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that the Hebrewes durſt not ſpeak, onely uſed in the ſingular number, to note the Unity of the Daity, appropriated to none but him, excluding all creatures, having Being independent in himſelfe, giving ſubſiſtence to all other things, faithfully performing his promiſes, and then ſhall not be that is All in All, made All, ſuſtaines All, is All-ſufficient, perform that to his Saints more than a World, or thouſands of worlds beſide?</p>
            <p>But what is the ſuit, that none but ſuch a Majeſty can grant? It is Light: not the Light created the firſt day, though that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livened the blinde <hi>Chaos,</hi> not thoſe on the fourth day; the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and the leſſer Lights hung up in the Canopy of Heaven, to enlighten the Theater of the World againſt mans entrance on the ſtage; not the force of reaſon implanted in man, though <hi>John</hi> 1.4. that be the Light of Man, not the Word of God;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:31589:12"/>though that be a Light unto our Feet; not the Miniſters of the Goſpel, though they (<hi>Math.</hi> 5.14.) be Lights of the World; not Chriſt alone (which truly is virtually All) though (<hi>John</hi> 1.8.) he be the true Light that enlightens every one that comes into the World; not that in Heaven (<hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.12.) the Inheritance of Saints in Light: but a Light that includes all theſe, that God, Chriſt Jeſus, his Word, his Miniſters, Light temporall, ſpirituall, eternall, are all ours, and that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here, by way of eminence, <hi>The Light of Gods Countenance;</hi> Chriſt was comforted in his Agony with the Light of Angels; <hi>Moſes</hi> his Face ſhined at the light of Gods hinder parts: O then, <hi>The Light of Gods Countenance!</hi> What Comfort brings it here, what eternall Bliſſe hereafter?</p>
            <p>Firſt, To prove that <hi>The Light of Gods Countenance</hi> is beyond all Prices unvaluable: Conſider,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. But what this <hi>Light</hi> was before ſinne put it out:</item>
               <item>2. What it coſt before it could be lighted againe:</item>
            </list>
            <p>Before ſinne put it out, it was Gods gracious favour in giving Man the comfortable uſe and intereſt in all Gods creatures, the Hoſts of Heaven, Sun, Moone and Starres, Foules of the Aire, Fiſhes of the Sea, Beaſts of the Barth, Creeping things, Herbs, Fruit, Corn, Wine, Oyle, were lines drawn from the infinite cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference of Gods goodneſſe, to the center of Mans felicity: Theſe were but blanks, beſides the Communion of Angels in Heaven, that ſeemes to be a Price, the bleſſed Viſion, eternall Union with God through Chriſt; a Price able to make Men and Angels ſound up their Trumpets of praiſe for ever.</p>
            <p>Secondly, what the lighting of it againe coſt: The Veſtals fire put our, might not be kindled but by the beams of the Sun, nor the light of Gods Grace, but by the obedience of his onely Sonne; Men, Angels, Bloud of Martyrs, Incence of Saints, a thouſand Worlds, ten thouſand Rivers of Oyl could not, but the Death of him that was the Lord of Life.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that it is beyond all contradictions impregnable the whole legion of Saints can witneſſe, it is Armour of Proofe, a ſtrong Tower, an invincible Fort, a rock of Salvation, that if Men, Devils, Behemoths, Leviathans, Loſſes, Diſeaſes, Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:31589:12"/>ſwarme about one like the flyes of <hi>Egypt;</hi> it will make one ſing under the whip at the ſtake, in the flames, make the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient laugh, when the ſpectator weeps, carry fraile flaſh ſinging and rejoycing through a world of bonds, rodds, ſwords, racks, wheeles, flames, ſtrappadoes, break thorow torments, armies tempeſts, floods, towards Heaven, ſhake off bonds, fetters, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles, and lead captivity captive.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That it is beyond all Conceptions tranſcendent, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Scripture, Teſtimony, Experience, can all tell; for Man or Angel to conceive or expreſſe the ſecret VVorking, the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Operation, the infinite ſplendor of Gods Grace, were to ſpan the Heavens with his Fingers, to graſp the waves of the Sea in his Fiſt, gather the waters of the Ocean into a bottle; Reaſon cannot fathome it, but is at a ſtand, Scripture expreſſes nothing ſo much as that it is unexpreſſible, Eye hath not ſeene, Eare hath not heard, neither hath it entred into the heart of Man, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. the Saints at the ſenſe of it are wrapt into an extaſie, <hi>Cherubims</hi> vaile their Faces, ſanctifying grace in man comes ſomewhat neare it, which cauſes Groans of the ſpirit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>utterable, Joy in the heart unſpeakable; and yet there is as great a diſ-proportion, as for one Starre that is enlightned by the Sun, to expreſſe the whole glory of the Sun; the world is but a printed Mappe, the reall Viſion is in Heaven; all creatures are but leaves in this imperfect Abridgement, the large Volume is ſealed up by him that keepes the keyes of life.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, That it is beyond all compariſons ſuperlatively great, the very devils can tel, and therefore to rob one man of it, will offer the whole world in counterpoiſe: we are like Sun Dials, unleſſe it ſhine, blaze Torches, Tapers, Candles, all Starres at ones, are of no uſe, flow Riches, Honour, Strength, Wives, Friends, Childen to our contentment; without that Sun it is ſtill night; they may be Copies of Gods Grace, but without Seale, Ciphers of no value, unleſſe the Unity of the Spirit be joyned with them: we cannot conceive ſo great a number of earthly things, but ſtill more may bee added, more may be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; but he that hath <hi>The Light of Gods Countenance</hi> is raviſhed in Spirit, cannot conceive more, hath contentment in heart, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deſire more, his cup does overflow.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:31589:13"/>
            <p>All this may bee confirmed by the Effects, and Fruits of it, by Examples; by the Effects, it's Light, that wee may ſee all things, expells Darkneſſe, that the miſt of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance vaniſhes, enlightens us that we are lights in our ſelves, that Reaſon, Will, Affections are improved, inflames our ſoules with the heat of Zeale, cauſes Faith, Hope, Charity, Patience, Long-ſuffering, bud out as herbes in the ſpirituall garden of the heart, if God lift up this Light over the Zenith of our ſoules, it cauſes theſe earthly ſhadowes of Honour, Beauty, Ambition, to be the ſhorteſt, our dayes of Comfort the longeſt, it is All things, a Caſtle to the Beſieged, Liberty to the Priſoner, a Father to the Fatherleſſe, a Husband to the Widow, Cloathes to the Naked, Bread to the Hungry, Health to the Sick, Oyntment to the Head, Oyle to the Face, Wine to the Heart, Marrow to the Bones, Strength to the Body, Comfort to the Sole, eternall Salvation to both Body and Sole.</p>
            <p>By examples, this Light held up, confirmed the bleſſed An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles, when the reſt fell into utter darkneſſe; guided <hi>Enoch</hi> that he walked with God, preſerved <hi>Noah</hi> in the Arke from the Flood, Jaſſwaged the heat of fire to the three Children in the Fornace, ſtopped the mouth of the Lions againſt <hi>Daniel</hi> in the Denne, made the Apoſtles ſing Pſalmes at midnight in the Gaoles, comforted the Martyrs in the Racks, Torments, Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, made <hi>Stephen</hi> in the midſt of helliſh paines to ſee Heaven open, as the Starre the wiſe men, guides all Saints to Chriſt in glory.</p>
            <p>All the reaſons wee will give of this point, is, that it is a Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing beyond all Reaſon, a Starre above our Firmament, that our underſtanding cannot calculate, our <hi>Jacobs</hi> Staffe cannot reach to; if we attaine to it by any meanes, it muſt be (with the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels) by <hi>Jacobs</hi> Ladder, Chriſt Jeſus: in that we cannot conceive it, it ariſes from the diſproportion betwixt our knowledge and it, in that it is our cheifeſt bliſſe, it's from the proportion betwivt our ſoules and it. We have done with the former, a word of the latter: Mans ſoule was created by God, nothing can ſatisfie it, but God hath ſome part of Gods image in it, like the pin of a D<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all, ſtill reſtleſſe, till it be fixed upon him the Pole; or <hi>Noahs</hi> Dove, ſtill flichring for the windowes of Heaven. Now Gods
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:31589:13"/>Grace is the earneſ, the ſeale in the forehead, the wedding gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which if we keep here, will aſſure us of all hereafter, the ſoule being in continuance eternall, in deſire infinite, cannot be contented with a finite: Man being of creatures the nobleſt, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reſt in an inferiour creature; but when the Creator ſupports the Creature, the cleareſt light ſhines in deepeſt darkneſſe, ſtrength uponlds weakneſſe; heaven is promiſed to him that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcued out of hell; and is not this able to ſway with all men in the world, with the wiſe men to forſake Heards, Cattell Friends, Lands, Revenews, and follow this Starre that guides us unto Chriſt, at his Fathers right hand in glory? Thus the reaſon, the uſes follow.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>Are all worldly things, as Gloe wormes, and rotten ſtocks in the dark, obſcured, when God puts brightneſſe of his face? Some men ſeem to have as ſincere joy in their Corne, Wine, Children, and in their eyes ſeem as bright Starres as Gods favour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, it is either in the night of their ignorance, before this morning Starre appeare in their hearts, or if after they are but <hi>Parelioſſes,</hi> which may ſhine, but it is when the true Sun is under a cloud: againe, what light they have it is borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the other by reflection.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Obj. <hi>The Saints, in whom this Light dwells, ſuffer afflictions, perſecutions, ſorrowes without, ſometimes pangs of Conſcience with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as though their light was put out in utter darkneſſe, whiles the Worldings rejoice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, though God ſometimes cover his face with clouds, yet in theſe ſtormes there are ſignes of his favour, which as the Rainbow ſhews ſome ſmall ſhower will follow, yet they are a ſure pledge, he will not utterly deſtroy them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Obj. <hi>If</hi> the light of Gods countenance <hi>ſo farre exceed all things, why doe ſo few men ſue for it, ſo many for earthly things?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer, they are like blazing Stars, and Meteors in the lower regions, that ſet all eyes at gaze; man by nature is blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with this <hi>ignis fatuus,</hi> or fooliſh fire, that leads him into every ditch: in that the Saints are freed, they are like the celeſtial Orbs, having a peculiar motion to themſelves, beſides the common mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>The ſecond uſe may let us ſee, wherein this grace of God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts, it's not his favour in beſtowing naturall endowments, as
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:31589:14"/>good temperature, in body, bloud, ſpirits, which hath the uſuall name of cheerfulneſſe; it's not a morall comfort at ſing from the exerciſe of high and heroicall morall vertues which breeds a kind of ſolace and contentment in the exerciſe, and work delight.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it's not a civil bleſſing conſiſting in honor, riches, wealth and other things temporall; for thus far the worlding may goe, but it's a ſpirituall favor ariſing from the preſence of Gods holy ſpirit, curing us, healing us, ſealing us to the everlaſting love of God in Chriſt Jeſus. See the links of this golden Chain; by this grace we are become new creatures, conceived of the Spirit, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.5. reconciled unto God in Chriſt, freed from Satans bondage, made ſpirituall Kings, and Prieſts, ſanctified by degrees, aſſured of ou a loption, encouraged to come to the throne of Grace, have peace of conſcience, joy in the holy Ghoſt, enjoys light that guides us in the narrow ſtraights of death, makes Saints ſhine at the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, as ſtarres carries us into heaven, where neither Sun nor Moon, but the Lambe ſhall enlighten us for ever.</p>
            <p>The third uſe may ſerve for humbling, from whence comes our foylings and faylings, our courage and valour, onely from Gods grace: 1. It makes us able to doe any thing; 2. fuffer any thing; 3. ſaves us from all things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Do any thing; ſubdue the fleſh, encounter Satan, conquer the world, when all friends forſake us at death, and follow us but to the grave; it makes our beds in ſickneſſe, cauſes us to dye ſof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſtands by us when we groan, and comforts u<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; heartens us up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on death when it is coming, and ſayes our Redeemer lives; whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpers us when we are departing, and ſayes our warfare is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed; lodges our body in the grave, as in a bed; mans our ſoule to heaven, makes it able to look God in the face without terror; nay, ſuſtains us when Riches, Parents, Husband, Friends, Breath, Life, even Patience, Hope, Faith have left us, in ſome meaſure it will not leave us.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſuffer any thing, Rage. Dragons, Bears, Lions, if God be pacified, frowne Tyrants and Executioners ſo he ſmile; man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling of Bodyes, ripping of Bowels, racking of Joynts, burning of Fleſh, boyling in Oyle become tolerable; when a murdering <hi>Theodorick</hi> ſees the face of a Man in the mouth of a Fiſh, it lets us ſee the power of God in weak fleſh; when <hi>Beſſus</hi> hears the cry of murder in the chattering of Birds, it ſhews the ſweet
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:31589:14"/>whiſpers of comfort in the ſoule: when <hi>Sanders</hi> runs over Iriſh mountaines out of his wits, it makes us run to God; when Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates call for hills and mountaines to cover them, it makes us look at the brightneſſe of Gods face (as the <hi>Gymnoſophiſts</hi> at the Sun) with undazled eyes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it ſaves us from all encounters, ſuppoſe Hell be let looſe upon us, the D<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vils let ſl p all their Doggs at once, ſome barke, ſome bite, all purſue; Gods grace ſtops all their mou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hs that they cannot hurt. This <hi>Light of Gods countenance</hi> is to us as a pillar of a cloud by day, a pillar of fire by night, ſtands ſtill, like the Sun to <hi>Joſhua,</hi> till we have vanquiſhed our bodily and ghoſtly enemies, when our joyes ſeeme to ſet, it turnes back (as the Sun to <hi>Hezekiah</hi>) that neither Plague, nor Sword, nor Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine of the Word, nor Death, nor Hell, nor Damnation ſhall prevaile over us.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, a word of Exhortation, and we have done. Now then (Brethren) Is not this Light worth the beholding? you cannot have alwayes comfort in Wealth, comfort in Health, comfort in Friends, Neighbours, Wives, Children, theſe be not alwayes, and while they be, they ſometimes miniſter matter of diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; yea ſometime their life and preſence doe diſcourage, but in the preſence of God is conſtant Peace, conſtant Comfort, and Joy to be found, he is conſtantly Good, True: O get this favou however you do, get it, and you ſhall have all, come what will come, this changes not; theſe Comforts in Chriſt are ſure, never ceaſe ſeeking, begging hearing, conferring, till his face ſhine upon you &amp; you be ſure of his love; you have ſeen the comforts of the world, you ſee how all ciſterns faile you;goe to the fountain in the word of God, in the Houſe of God, in the Favour of God, you ſhall have comfort in his Light, you ſhall ſee light, when others nothing but Darkneſſe round about. O then, thou that ſitteſt in darkneſſe of Affliction, darkneſſe of Poverty, D<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bt, in the darkneſſe of Temptation, of Sin, thou that ſeeſt no light, none within thee, none without thee, none in thy Soul, none in thy Mind, none in thine Eſtate, Friends; ariſe, put on Beauty, come into the Light, ſtand up from the Dead; dead Comforts, dead Companions, dead Works; and the Lord ſhall lift up <hi>the light of his countenance upon thee for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:31589:15"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31589:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
